<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of the affaires betwixt the Emperor and King of Bohemia, and their confederates as it hath beene very truely related, by certaine letters sent by persons of extraordinary qualitie, &amp;c. Together vvith the occurrents lately happened in the armies of Generall Veere, and the princes of the Union, and Spinola. Translated out of the French, and High Dutch coppies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00681</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837782</idno>
  <idno type="VID">2124</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248560835</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10815</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S101979</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99837782e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of the affaires betwixt the Emperor and King of Bohemia, and their confederates as it hath beene very truely related, by certaine letters sent by persons of extraordinary qualitie, &amp;c. Together vvith the occurrents lately happened in the armies of Generall Veere, and the princes of the Union, and Spinola. Translated out of the French, and High Dutch coppies.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ (=C4?) A-B⁴ C⁴ (-C4); ² A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>"The copie of a letter written from the Duke of Iegersdorff, generall of the armie in Lusatia, to the King of Bohemia" begins new register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1526-  --  Sources.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Holy Roman Empire --  History --  Ferdinand II, 1619-1623 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:1"/>
            <p>THE Present State of the Affaires betwixt the Emperor and <hi>King of</hi> BOHEMIA, <hi>and their</hi> Confederates, as it hath beene very Truely related, by certaine Letters <hi>Sent by Persons of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> qualitie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Together With the Occurrents lately hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Armies of Generall VEERE, the Princes of the VNION, and SPINOLA,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated out of the</hi> French, <hi>and High</hi> Dutch <hi>Coppies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, 1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2124:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the most Excellent and Illustrious</hi> Prince and Lord FREDERICKE, by the Grace of GOD <hi>King</hi> of BOHEMIA, <hi>Count Palatine</hi> of the RHINE, Prince <hi>Elector</hi> of the Sacred <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, <hi>Duke</hi> of BAVARIA, <hi>Marquesse</hi> of MORAVIA, <hi>Duke</hi> of LVTZELBVRG, and SILESIA, <hi>Marquesse</hi> of LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SATIA, our most deare <hi>Lord, Brother, Gossip, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> and <hi>Confederate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GReat KING: The hopes and desires of your Majesties Friends and our Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, haue met at last with Peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment: whilest all the faithfull and well affected people, States, and Nobility, ioyning hearts and Voyces, haue now in the end with one consent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp the Gouernment of this Kingdome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our handes: not doubting of our care and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to protect and defend the same; A worke whome none but men depriued of reason will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vnto other then the immediate power of God: Whither for our owne good, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice; hee that disputeth it; boldely inquireth after the insearchable counsels of God: But it is enough that no times from the Foundation of the World haue giuen examples or testimony of a more hearty and vnanimous Consent, in the Defence of true Religion, the Loue of God and the maintaining of Christian Liberty: then
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2124:3"/>are these that hath thus brought foorth two such Kinges: Wherefore since wee are thus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed and called foorth, let Vs with Care and wisdome boldely enter into the Defence of the common Cause, and in the name thereof wee sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute your Majesty; Nothing; no not our owne Blood binding vs to more Loue and Seruice then wee professe to your Majesty, desiring but so much Honour as to haue time and place to agree of a meeting, where sincerely and as Brothers wee may Conferre of the Affaires of Religion, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique weale of our Countryes: Whereof shortly and with speede I shall write more at large to your Majesty:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Brother Gossip and Confederate, GABRIELL.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uisolij</hi>
                  <date>28. of <hi>August.</hi> 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2124:3"/>
            <head>Serenissimo Principi ac Domino <hi>Frederico</hi> Dei G. Regi <hi>Bohemiae,</hi> Comiti Palatino <hi>Rheni,</hi> S.R.I. Principi <hi>Electori,</hi> Duci <hi>Bauariae,</hi> Marchioni <hi>Morauiae, Lucemb.</hi> &amp; <hi>Silesiae</hi> Duci, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiae{que}</hi> Marchioni, &amp;c. <hi>Domino</hi> Fratri Compatri Vicino &amp; Confederato nobis Charissimo.</head>
            <p>SErenissime Rex Domine Frater Compater Charissime. Satisfactumiam est desideratissimis tam vestrae Dilectionis quam omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Confoederatorum nostrorum votis dum videlicet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersi fideles Status &amp; Ordines nostri, paribus votis &amp; saffragijs personam nostram ad Regni huius fastigiam evehendo, nostrae sese curae regimini &amp; Conseruationi subijcere nequaquam dubetauerint. Opus hoc solius Dei esse nullus fueri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nisi penitus visu mente{que} captus, qui inficias ire possit. Bonone verò nostro an malo, quis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perscrutabilia Deiconsilia inuestiget? Sufficit nullum se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum ab orbe condito vidisse saltem talta tempora, qui tam coniunctissimis animis, qua in Deum, qua in purio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Orthodoxam religionem, qua in restitutionem liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum publicarum, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os Reges tam inaudito &amp; stupendo exemplo produxissent. Quaecum ita sint, tanto iam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiore cordis intimi affectu remcausam{que} communem aggrediamur oportet, eo{que} nomineid vnicè à V. Dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne effl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gitamus, nos non aliter ergà se affict quam ergà proprium &amp; si quid maius dici possit, Sanguinem, certò
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2124:4"/>sibi persuasum habere velit, nihil{que} iam cogitare amplius, quam vt occasio &amp; locus commodus suppetat, quo mutuo congressu res nostras sincere inuicem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municare liceat, de quo propediem ad V. Dilectionem su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus perscripturi. Reliqua cum nuper per Dominum Plesseum, tum praesenti que{que} Barone ab Hogieowa in priuatis colloquijs vltrò citro{que} agitatis, Dilectionis V. referenda concredimus. Quibus candem fidem indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am adhibere &amp; nos amore continuo prosequi non cessabit. Deus Dilect. V. conseruit diutissisime regnantem &amp; flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem. Dabantur Nouisolij <hi>28.</hi> Augusti, <hi>1620.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Dilectionis V.</hi> Frater, Compater &amp; Confoede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur Studiosissimus: <hi>GABRIELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2124:4"/>
            <head>From <hi>PRAGVE</hi> the First of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> St. N. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> hath now openly Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himselfe an Enemy to the King and all these Countryes, intending to doe with vs, as hee hath already done vpon the Riuer of <hi>Ense,</hi> and as hee alledges put the Imperiall Commission in execution, which these his Designes he hath made manifest by his Letter written to our King, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that by his owne hand writ, hee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribes, <hi>Your true Cosen and Friend:</hi> MAXI: Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting that hee will remaine so still; But the Kings Majesty hath answered him brauely, letting him know that for all his Menaces hee doth not meane to goe backe from his true grounded Resolution, desiring him to view and read that of his Majesties Deduction, wherein is plainly to be seene the Iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and clearenes of their Cause.</p>
            <p>This Duke of of <hi>Bauier</hi> hath a part of his Army neare the borders of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> neare vnto <hi>Newhause</hi> and <hi>Wittingaw,</hi> and another part hee hath sent to <hi>Buequoy,</hi> a third part hee hath left in <hi>Austria</hi> vpon the <hi>Ense.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our great Army is yet in <hi>Austria,</hi> where it is day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increased by the comming of the <hi>Hungarians:</hi> our other Army vnder the Conduct of the Count
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2124:5"/>of <hi>Thurn,</hi> and in his absence led by <hi>Mansfield,</hi> lyes now about <hi>Weseley</hi> two miles from <hi>Newhause,</hi> and so much from <hi>Bodeweis,</hi> in that Army there is 4. regiments of Foote, the Count of <hi>Mansfields,</hi> Collonell <hi>Grayes,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Weymars,</hi> and <hi>Setouns,</hi> and Collonell <hi>Franks,</hi> also 6. Cornets of Horse, and 1000. <hi>Hungarian</hi> Horsmen, and our Country Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ioynes also with them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bauarian</hi> will haue very shortly <hi>Hungarian</hi> guests in his Country, that will not be very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him, and euery man wonders that hee would enterprise any thing against this Country hauing no Iust cause, since alwayes hee protested Neuterality. But it seemes his Protestations and faire promises were alwayes <hi>Iesuiticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> hath very respectiuely heard our Ambassadors, and also receiued his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Letters, But all his Answer is hee must obey the Imperiall Commission, and so seaze vpon this Crowne for the Emperour: whereupon he gathers his Army together, bending towards <hi>Aussig</hi> or <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia</hi> the Superior. GOD the most just Iudge, will in mercy looke downe vpon vs, and according to the equity of our iust Cause helpe vs, since our Friends, Kinsmen, and Allies, and also those of our Religion, not onely leaues vs in our necessitie and takes part with Papists, but also rewards vs euill for Good, and are become our enemies without all cause.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2124:5"/>
            <p> Yet both <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Bauier,</hi> stayes for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Spinola,</hi> and then they meane vtterly to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe vs, they are agreed to meete at <hi>Prague</hi> on Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas day, But with Gods grace they shall find good resistance, and it may bee (if they Dine with vs) they shall pay surely for their Dinner, and whatsoeuer mischiefe or effusion of Blood will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue vpon this, his Majestie protests before God and all the World that hee is most Innocent thereof, Since it is most manifest his Majesty did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude himselfe to this Crowne, neither by Bribery, Corruption, or any worldly respect, either of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or profite, but was freely Elected of a free State, being oppressed with Tyrannie both in their Bodyes and Consciences. His Maiesty protests al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so hee did take this Crowne to holde it intire to the Romaine Empire, which was euen ready to haue embraced the Protection of the Barbarous <hi>Turke,</hi> to the great losse, shame and disgrace of all Christians.</p>
            <p>Wee sent 5000. <hi>Silesians</hi> together with the Country Soldiers, towardes the borders of <hi>Misnia</hi> and <hi>Lusatia,</hi> there is some feare of the <hi>Polonian</hi> who being solicited by the <hi>Saxon,</hi> may happely inuade <hi>Silesia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi> is gone towardes <hi>Presburgh,</hi> where he is to bee Crowned since now the generall Estates of that Kingdome haue accepted him for their King, hee desires earnestly to haue a personall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2124:6"/>meeting with our Generall the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> for hee hath spoyled all with the Emperour, who hoped other dealing at his hands.</p>
            <p>His Army he hath Deuided in three partes, one to stay and waite vpon the <hi>Turke</hi> and <hi>Polonian</hi> (if they should attempt any thing) another are fallen in in <hi>Stiria,</hi> the Bishopricke of <hi>Saltzburgk,</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaria,</hi> where now they are ruyning and spoyling all, the third part hee hath sent to Ioyne with our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, God turne all thinges to the best, for those goodly Countryes are likely to bee vtterly ruyned. His Maiesty vses all meanes to hinder this, but wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men will not heare their owne welfare. The Romish Priests begins to bee Iealous of the <hi>Bauari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who they see lookes more to his owne profit then the welfare of their Church, for hee takes all Vpper <hi>Austria</hi> to his owne obedience, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that hee promised to the Pope and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour the contrary, vpon which hee hath receiued great summes of money from them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Saxony</hi> begins to doe the like; if hee can winne any thing hee certainly will restore so much to the Emperour as he shall not haue any neede of: hee hath sent Lerters to the Count of <hi>Schlik</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of <hi>Lusatia,</hi> who returnes him no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer but the Cannon roaring to remaine and dye Constant to his King and Countrey, leauing the Issue to the Almighty God.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Bauier</hi> hauing receiued his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2124:6"/>resolute Answer hee made no reply, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently with 10000. Foote, and 10. peeces of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Marched towards <hi>Newhause,</hi> thinking to haue taken the Towne, but finding <hi>Mansfield</hi> there with his Regiments, was glad to get backe againe with his Honour towardes <hi>Weidhofenn</hi> in <hi>Austria,</hi> where the Count of <hi>Mansfield</hi> with 8000. Foot and 1500. Horse persues him at the heeles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucquoy</hi> so soone as hee had receiued the <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> helpe, sent for his Artillery to <hi>Crembs,</hi> what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize he hath in hand time will tell vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saxony</hi> hauing 7000. men approaches towards <hi>Bantzen</hi> in <hi>Lusatia,</hi> and hath sent a Currier to the Gouernour, desiring them to call a generall mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting where his Highnes will first show vnto them the Emperours Commission, wishing him and them to yeeld Obedience thereto, but hee hath desired first to bee resolued from the King at <hi>Prague,</hi> whose Resolution is, that the Marquisse of <hi>Iegersdorffe</hi> with all the <hi>Silesian</hi> Forces, and 6000. <hi>Hungarian</hi> Horse shall presently withstand him, so in this time our Army is growne too great for him.</p>
            <p>The next Sunday his Maiesty with all his Court doth receiue the holy Communion, and presently thereafter Marches towardes his Army, where in person he is to meet with <hi>Bethlehem Gabor,</hi> the Horsemen appointed for the Guard of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties person are this day Muster'd, and certainly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2124:7"/>they are a most braue Company. We shall shortly heare of strange alterations.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter from <hi>Vienna</hi> the second of September, <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>This day the Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> set vpon <hi>Dampier</hi> his Campe setting Fire on the same, put all to the Sword, and tooke all their baggage and Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Buequoy</hi> was there also and fled towards the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarian</hi> Army. The Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> and the Count <hi>Hoenlce,</hi> are followed them with their whole Army.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>From. <hi>Wien</hi> the <hi>3</hi> of September.</head>
            <p>This night there came three Posts to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour one after another from <hi>Bucquoyes</hi> Army, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling how the <hi>Bohemians</hi> had fallen in vpon his Quarter being at <hi>Egenberg</hi> and hath set the same on Fire, for they priuily in the night put their Army in readines, and so set Fire on their owne Quarter, whereupon <hi>Bucquoy</hi> thinking them to haue fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to follow, but or euer he was aware the Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> was in his Quarter, and hath slaine 400. men, burnt &amp; taken all his Baggage and Munition, with many Prisoners, hee himselfe beeing sore Wounded is escaped and no man can tell whither, but by conjecture hee is fledde to the <hi>Bauarian</hi> Army.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2124:7"/>
            <p> Heere is not any great likelyhood of agreement betwixt the Papists and Protestants, for although that the Protestants haue promise of his Imperiall Maiesty not to bee molested, yet they will not be contented with his Maiesties resolution granted them the 13. of March, 1619. Therefore they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made choyse of certaine Commissioners on both sides to treate of agreement, his Imperiall Maiesty hath sent them worde to leaue all Disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and looke how to withstand the great Force of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> promising to bee helping vnto them all that he can or may.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter from <hi>Vien</hi> the <hi>5.</hi> of September. St. N. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>As his Imperiall Maiesty heard the Propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Demaunds of the Estates of <hi>Hungary,</hi> hee was mightily enraged, and would not graunt them any of their Requests, which caused them proceed sodainly to the Coronation of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> who was Elected the 25. of August, and the 9<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> of this Month to be Crowned, which sodaine and vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for Change hath not a little stirred his Maiesty, who presently hath sent. Worde to <hi>Spaine, Pope, Bauier,</hi> and <hi>Saxon,</hi> so that <hi>Dampier</hi> his going for <hi>Hungarie</hi> goes slowly forwards, The Lord <hi>Breuner</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Raab</hi> is made Generall for his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Maiesty in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and <hi>Esterhasie,</hi> and <hi>Palfie,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2124:8"/>with other <hi>Hungarians</hi> to the number of 10000. who yet holdes for the Emperour, these will goe to <hi>Hungarie</hi> if they can: there is heere great terrour and feare for <hi>Bethlehem</hi> his great Army, who with 20000. Horsemen, is fallen in in <hi>Stiria</hi> and <hi>Bauier:</hi> all Passages are beset in the best fashion that may bee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bethlehem</hi> with his Wife, is ariued at <hi>Presburgh</hi> in most great Pompe and Tryumph, who after his Coronation goes presently to meete with the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian,</hi> who hath also a mighty Army, and not likely to goe out of <hi>Austria</hi> this yeare, they haue all necessaries plenty, where to the contrary our men Dies, and in 3. Monthes hath not receiued any Pay, God helpe vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>From <hi>Franckfort</hi> the <hi>11.</hi> of September. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The 8<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> of this Month arriued heere the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Embassadour with a great Trayne, and the next day tooke Boate for <hi>Collen</hi> and so towards the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> The English Embassadour was heere also, who goes towardes <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Bauier,</hi> their Commission is to treate of Peace, there comes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day more supply to the Vnited Princes, and <hi>Landgraue Mauritz</hi> of <hi>Hesson,</hi> hath sent 2000. men to their Assistance, so that by Gods grace they are able to withstand <hi>Spinola.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2124:8"/>
            <head>Another Letter from the Campe of the <hi>Vnion,</hi> the <hi>12.</hi> of September. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Yesterday <hi>Spinola</hi> left his Campe and Marched from the <hi>Nekkerheim</hi> Hill towards <hi>Crentznach,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a great many Souldiers and all his Carriage standing behinde the Hill, to make vs thinke hee would not mooue from thence, in the meane time he caused to blowe vp the Port of <hi>Crentznach</hi> and so seazed by Force on the Towne. The next day Captaine <hi>Berkstadt</hi> with 3. Cornets of Horse set vppon the Reargard of <hi>Spinola's</hi> Horsemen, and tooke one Cornet of <hi>Spinola's</hi> with many Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and one Mule richly charged, all which was brought to <hi>Oppenheim.</hi> The next day there was certaine Villages set on Fire, which made the Princes raise their Army and March towards <hi>Alt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zey,</hi> where <hi>Spinola</hi> meanes to come and intrench himselfe, so to waite some oportunity for to take <hi>Wormbs,</hi> but they haue taken in our men for defence of their Citty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>From the <hi>Palatinate</hi> the <hi>12.</hi> of September.</head>
            <p>After that <hi>Spinola</hi> had taken <hi>Crentznach,</hi> the next day the Prince of <hi>Espinoy</hi> who led with him some Horsemen and the Marquisse of <hi>Malespina,</hi> was by Colonell <hi>Obertraut</hi> incountred, and hauing lost 60. Horse was together with <hi>Malespina</hi> taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2124:9"/>and since <hi>Spinola</hi> hath quitted <hi>Crentznach</hi> with losse of some men, and the Arch-Duke his Confessor beeing a Counsellor of Warre (a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession against his profession) is taken Prisoner and led to <hi>Heidelbergh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another from <hi>Oppenheim</hi> the <hi>12.</hi> of September. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>As <hi>Spinola</hi> had on Thursday last taken <hi>Crentz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach</hi> with little losse of men on both sides, that same Night hee caused a great part of his Army march towardes <hi>Altzey,</hi> which caused our Generall about midnight to march with 40. Cornets of Horse and 3. peece of Cannon directly towards <hi>Wormbs,</hi> Friday morning Captaine <hi>Obertrant</hi> and Lieutenāt <hi>Paff</hi> with 220. Harquebusiers, did charge the Prince of <hi>Espinoy</hi> who was conuoying the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with two Companies of Curriers, and after the losse of some 10. of our men, and 60. of theirs, our men tooke <hi>Espinoy</hi> and the Marquisse of <hi>Males<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina</hi> Prisoners with many others. Our Generall came the last night backe to the Campe, and the Marquisse of <hi>Baden</hi> stayed without all night with the Cauallerie.</p>
            <p>It is supposed that <hi>Spinola</hi> hath taken <hi>Altzey</hi> because it is neere <hi>Wormbes,</hi> which makes our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall carefull to defend the Citty, now wee are all declared Eenemies to <hi>Spinola</hi> and therefore wee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2124:9"/>must by Gods assistance looke to our selues, <hi>Spino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> thought to haue deceiued vs by a Stratagem, for he caused all his Army to March thinking that wee would follow him, to the intent that if wee had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, hee would in the night haue returned and so haue taken our Bridge, which being knowne by a Prisoner taken, the Generall caused 2000. Foote to goe towardes our Bridge for the Defence of the same.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>From his <hi>Excellence</hi> his Campe the <hi>16.</hi> of September. <hi>1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Since that Count <hi>Henry</hi> with Generall <hi>Veer,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from hence towards the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> we heare that he goes towards <hi>Gulich</hi> and the Riuer of <hi>Eyffell, Meyuelt,</hi> and so ouer the <hi>Mosell,</hi> through the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of <hi>Summiren</hi> and so to the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> where the Princes meetes them, so that in short time wee shall heare of their prosperous proceedings.</p>
            <p>Sunday last <hi>Don Lewis de Velasco</hi> came to <hi>Weesell,</hi> and so stayed two dayes, and afterward departed.</p>
            <p>In the meane time his Excellence hath Fortified two good Forts, euery one hauing 17. peece of Ordinance, meaning to stay there this Winter till the Truce bee out.</p>
            <p>Two dayes agoe the Gouernour of <hi>Weesell</hi> sent his Secretary to his Excellence, demaunding of him why hee Fortified there so neare <hi>Weesell,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2124:10"/>who answered because there was roome enough there, and if he pleased hee might come and Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie also.</p>
            <p>Since which time his Excellence was certified of the recouery of <hi>Crentznach,</hi> and of the taking of the Arch-Duke his Confessor, who is one of the Counsaile of Warre to <hi>Spinola,</hi> hee is carryed to the Castle of <hi>Heidelburgh,</hi> there to remaine till further aduisement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2124:10"/>
            <head>A Briefe Collection of certaine Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to diswade the Emperour from giuing Credit vnto those violent Counsailes which hath beene giuen him, to proceed by way of <hi>Ban</hi> and <hi>Proscription</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Vnited</hi> Princes and <hi>Protestant</hi> States, especially against the <hi>Elector PALATINE;</hi> being Presented and deliuered vnto the Ambassadours of <hi>France,</hi> at the Assembly of the saide Princes and States, which was held at <hi>Vlme. 1620.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrst, It would bee a manifest injustice, for the Emperour to proceed so extreamly as by way of <hi>Ban</hi> and <hi>Proscription</hi> to Denounce against the Princes and Protestant States Vnited, and namely against the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> at this present King of BOHEMIA: Because his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty in accepting the Crowne which was Presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him by the Estates of the said Kingdome, hath committed neither Crime nor offence against Emperour or Empire: Hauing alwayes beene of the opinion and still beleeuing so; that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was vacant at the houre of his Accepting of it: which by a Declaration publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in the Assembly of the said States and Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated Prouinces hath beene manifested out of the groundes of their natiue Law and free Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as also for many other reasons amply expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in their last lustification lately set forth, enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with many Discourses and proofes to make vp
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2124:11"/>the better a finall Answer vnto all Objections and Informations giuen or published to the Contrary, as also to all false Suppositions, Apoligies and other discourses Printed or Diuulged within the Empire or without.</p>
            <p>Secondly, because in the Accepting of the saide Kingdome, his Majesty hath not so much looked vpon his owne Greatnes, Profite and particular Cōmodity, but vnto the preseruation rather of the said Crowne, which by the extremities &amp; miseries it was now reduced vnto, was thereby in danger to fall into the hand of a Stranger, and vnchristian Enemy, to the prejudice of all Christendome and especially of the Holy Empire: Thus the now King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> finding himselfe bound by Oath and duty vnto the Empire, to take Care thereof as farre as in him lay, and perceiuing that their Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and miseries had made them take a resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neuer to Admit or acknowledge the Emperour for their King, as also for the safegard of many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent soules, dayly and hourely exposed vnto all the miseries and cruelties of a Warre and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Souldier, thus was perswaded to accept of the Crowne, by which followed a cessation of Warre and the Effussion of so much Christian Blood: for which hee seemeth rather to deserue well of his Countrey, then to bee lyable vnto any aspersion or imputation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his Imperiall Maiesty beeing a Party, cannot be Iudge in this busines, neither as King of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2124:11"/>
               <hi>Bohemia</hi> not as Emperour: But suppose it were not so, yet could hee not vndertake the decission of a busines of this Consequence, against a principall member of the Empire without the rest of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors should there Preside and concurre: And howsoeuer, although some of the Princes Electors excluding others, would pretend to haue taken these thinges into their Electorall Consideration, yet will not that serue the turne: For the States of <hi>Behemia</hi> and the Incorporated Countryes, haue Protested before GOD and Men, against that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just proceeding that was held by the said Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall Princes Electors, against the aduice and Counsell of the Ambassadours of the secular Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors, neither lending their Eare nor Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vnto the Grieuances and Complaints of the Ambassadours, and Deputies that were sent vnto them, at their last meeting or Dyete at <hi>Franckfort:</hi> Insomuch as denying them all Iustice contrary to the Law of Nations they were rejected and sent backe: Nay which is more, all their remonstrances and grieuances which they exhibited by Bill vnto the Prince Elector of <hi>Mense,</hi> Chancellour of the Empire, were by him suppressed &amp; not deliuered vp vnto the Electorall Colledge to aduise of, as had been very fit and necessary for the publique Good.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that Precipitation of Iudgment is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the Lawes and Constitutions of the Empire, and vnto the Imperiall Capitulation vnto which the Emperour hath taken a solemne Oath.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2124:12"/>
            <p> Fiftly, as his Imperiall Majesty is bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Empire in Peace and repose, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the generall Good of the whole Body, before his owne priuate; So hath he Confirmed it and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured it vnto the Princes and vnited States, and to their Correspondents in the last assembly at <hi>Norem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> from the mouth of Count <hi>de Qollerne</hi> his Ambassadour: That hee neither thought or would that any of the said States or Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, should bee incommoded or suffer any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or inconuenience, for his particular assuring them that hee would auow what his Ambassadour had deliuered vnto them: as also it is Registred and recorded in the Acts of the said Assembly.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, If the Emperour should oppresse the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Subiects of the Palitanate, yet that is not a means to quiet the affayres of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> that would onely be able to disturbe and not to extinguish the fire that endangers the Kingdome, and probably endanger the whole Empire: which his Maiesty, could not doe with a safe Conscience, and without Contradiction to his Holy Oath, the distast of men and the displeasure of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Seauenthly, the Princes and vnited States, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well refuse to interest themselues in the defence of the Palatinate, holding the same resolution that they haue already taken, with the rest of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Correspondent States, as they haue let the Ambassadours and the Emperour himselfe to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand: In respect of the straite Vnion and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2124:12"/>that they hold with the Palitanate, the which was principally made in respect of the euill procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Imperiall Court and Iustice: of which they haue so often Complained, as a thing which doth prejudice the Liberty, Priuiledges and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of their Principalities and Dominions: Insomuch that it would be the griefe of Griefes, if his Imperiall Maiesty should so degenerate from his Predecessors, as to begin his Kingdome with so violent proceedings, so estranged from the forme of Law and Equity, without hearing the Reasons and Iustifications of the other party, a thing so contrary vnto the Constitutions and Decrees of the Empire.</p>
            <p>Eightly, The said Vnited Princes and their As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociates are equally obliged by reason of State, as also out of the Oath they haue taken to the Holy Empire, to prouide against the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Ciuill Warre, which cannot well bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Palatinate, but it will reach forth and extend it selfe vnto the whole Empire their Goods, Lands and Liues.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, euen as for neerenes and Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood sake those of the Religion could not, nor would not willingly suffer that one should make warre against the Romane Catholiques, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine with their Countries; so out of the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration those of the Religion beeing so mixed and linked together cannot well permit the Fier should be put to one house for feare of consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2124:13"/>burning the rest: for which cause it would be more profitable that euen the Roman Catholiques in this case should haue a fellow feeling, and suffer with those of the Religion: for all extremities are accompanied with dangerous Chanses &amp; changes.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, it is a great encouragement to Ingage and imbarque all Princes, Friends and Allyes, to bring their friendly Armes and Assistance vnto the heart of the Empire: The Declaration that the King of Great <hi>Britanny</hi> hath made to the Arch-Duke <hi>Albert,</hi> videlicet: That hee will neuer aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, forsake, or leaue out of his care the Countries State, and Possessions his Children are borne vnto, as also hee will lend his Assistance vnto the States and Princes Vnited his Allyes and Friends: whose Maiesty if they shall Incence, may haue a iust reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and take Reuenge vppon the Terretories of the House of <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This that hath bene written sufficiently proueth that the way of <hi>Ban</hi> and <hi>Proscription,</hi> much lesse the execution of the Emperours injust mandates of <hi>Via facti &amp; armorum</hi> against the <hi>Palatinat,</hi> cannot proue the meane to redresse or to establish a Peace &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility in the Empire, to the Care of which his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maiesty is so strictly by Oath called vnto: But it would rather be fit for his Imperiall Maiesty to forsake the euill Counsels of those men which ayme at nought but the rayne and destruction of <hi>Germauy,</hi> by the Introduction of a Forraine Power and Strange Nation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:13"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter written from the Duke of Iegersdorff, Generall of the Armie in Lusatia, to the King of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most gracious KING,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YEsternight, about tenne of the clocke, there came to mee one of the Captaines of the Towne of Bautzen, who had beene once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with mee; he tells me, that with great danger he came thorow the Woods and Morasses, being followed by the enemie two miles. Moreouer, being tells mee, that vpon the thirteenth of these, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie had raysed a skonce, and planted foure peeces of Ordnance; vpon the foureteenth, he approched to the Towne-ditch, he played with his Ordnance all the day long, but did no great harme. About nine of the clocke at night, Colonell <hi>Goldsteins</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment begun an assault, meaning to haue taken the suburbes; the assault continued from tenne of the clocke at night, till three in the morning: and (as the prisoners reports) they lost three hundred men, and their Colonels Lieutenant was shot in the Leg; of our men there was but two slaine, and thirtie hurt. In the time of the assault, there was by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence a barrell of Powder set on fire by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, which did them great harme; which our men seeing, they presently fallied out, and killed thirtie, and tooke seuen and twentie prisoners: our men tooke also a great many Muskets and Pikes, with
<pb facs="tcp:2124:14"/>other Armes; and, which was strange, the enemie had left two Wagons charged with Spades and Mattocks, and great Iron barres, and a barrell of Musket bullets. And my horsmen tooke yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night three prisoners, who affirme the same; and being further examined, they say, that they are but badly payed, getting but tenne or twelue grosches at a time, by way of loane: also they say, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor hath thirtie sixe cornets of Horse, together with the Countrie troupes, and two Regiments of foot, with foure Ensignes of Countrie-people, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting euerie day new supply; and that their soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers at the assault calling for bullets, had such gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, as they could make no vse of at all.</p>
            <p>These occurrences I thought good to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with your Maiestie. <hi>Datum Goerlitz,</hi> the sixteenth of September, at nine of the clock before noone.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:14"/>
            <head>The true Copie of a Letter, written by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Counsellors and Officers of the Kingdome of Bohemia, &amp;c. To the Illustrious Prince Elector of Saxonie, &amp;c. Desiring and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishing his Highnesse, not to attempt any thing against the Kings Maiestie of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, and the incorporated Countries thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed, neyther to send any forces out of his Territories, to the seruice of the Pope and the Spaniards, to the preiudice of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Princes, and whole Empire.</head>
            <head type="sub">ALSO, <hi>The Copie of another Letter from the foresaid Counsellors and Officers of Bohemia, to the trayned Souldiers in</hi> Engernn, <hi>and other Townes in the Electors Countrie of Saxonie: Dated at Prague the fourth of September,</hi> 1620.</head>
            <p>MOst Illustrious Prince, our humble seruices remembred, wishing your Highnesse all health and happinesse; These are to let you know, that being at this present enformed by <hi>Adolff,</hi> Baron of Gerstorff, Counsellor and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour in Vpper Lusatia for his Maiestie of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, that your Highnesse wisheth him to sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:2124:15"/>the people of that Countrie to assemble in Counsell together, and to insinuate an Imperiall Commission vnto them: as also that the said Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour certifieth vs, that your Highnesse forces are marching forward towards the borders of the said Countrie, whereby wee may easily and euidently perswade our selues to what purpose the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission tendeth; for that our Ambassadours beeing lately with your Highnesse at Dresden, (contrarie to our expectations) found your Graces minde to bee wholly alienated from vs, and that now you are of another opinion then at the beginning your Highnesse made shew of: as also that your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse hath neuer beene truely enformed, touching our Apologie and Deductions sent out, and manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted to all Christendome; otherwise it were impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible that your Highnesse, beeing a Protestant Prince-Elector, (whose famous Predecessours, for vpholding and maintenance of the Gospel, and their ancient freedome, haue not spared to hazzard their Lands, Liues, and Goods, in the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, against the Spanish and Iesuiticall tyrannie; as also, that your Highnesse holdeth and enioyeth so large a Territorie and Possession of this Crowne:) If these things were truely related and represented vnto you, would euer haue embraced the execution of such an Imperiall Commission, wrested and wrung by papisticall and Spanish counsels from his Imperiall Maiestie: by your Highnesse meanes (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so long atime) casilier to enforce the execution of the Articles of the Councell of Trent, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="tcp:2124:15"/>all the true professors of the Gospell in the Empire, then euer it could haue beene done before: which their designe hath manifestly and oftentimes beene published and set forth in Print by diuers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisticall Authors, declaring <hi>Sectarios Sectariorum auxilijs opprimendos esse:</hi> which <hi>Paulus Windec,</hi> in his Book entituled, <hi>Deliberatio de Haeresibus extirpandis,</hi> plainely expresseth: and the daily practises and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Papists more then sufficiently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessing their secret intents. And the examples of their proceedings and dealing with the Townes of Wesell, and Donawert, whose miseries are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest to our eyes; as also the late most bloudie Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre (made by the Spaniards in the Popes name at Veltlin) where (to the horror of posteritie) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Sermon, they most cruelly murthered and hewed both Men, Women, and innocent Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in pieces, (thereby manifestly discouering their pretence touching the finall suppression of that free Nation,) plainely shew what wee are to expect from them by these dealings. And the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists in all places bragge and boast thereof in such manner, that it is certainely written from Rome, that those of the League in the Empire (touching matters of Bohemia) should not proceede openly therein as they doe, till they had first wonne your Highnesse to agree and consent to be on their side. And therein haue now proceeded so farre, that your Highnesse is content to yeeld in all things to the Spirituall Electors, and so to accommodate your selfe to the will and pleasure of the Pope, and
<pb facs="tcp:2124:16"/>his adherents. But howsoeuer it shall please God to bring the issue of these things to passe, your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse must be well aduised, and consider, that if you enter into Armes against those of the Religion, the innocent bloud that shall be shed therein, will (by God) one day be required at your Highnesse hands. Withall, we cannot by any meanes see nor find, that such like Imperiall Commissions giuen out and thundred against this Kingdome, and the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces incorporated thereunto, can with equitie and iustice be any wayes iustified: not onely in respect of the manifest exemption thereof, but also <hi>ob noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium defectum Iurisdictionis:</hi> and likewise that all the sayd proceedings (although no such considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were made) directly, <hi>è diametro,</hi> are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to all godly and humane Lawes, and especially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the capitulations of the Roman Empire, and the fundamentall Lawes and Constitutions of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And it is most strange, and a thing neuer hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heard of, that an Emperour of Rome, (in his owne priuate quarrell touching the House of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria, and no wayes concerning the Empire,) should be Plaintife, Iudge, and Executioner; as also, that some others of the States (no Imperiall Assembly being formerly called, nor any lawfull proceeding before the same being made, nor processe Imperiall sent forth) should of malice take part with him in his priuate Austrian pretences, and ayde and assist him therein. But if it were a thing that concerned the Empire it selfe, then in duety euery man were
<pb facs="tcp:2124:16"/>bound to lay his helping hand thereunto, for that, <hi>Quod omnes tangit ab omnibus tractari debeat.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men must of necessitie make their account, that whatsoeuer hapneth to the Crowne of Bohemia by these proceedings of the House of Austria, will in like manner fall vppon the Romane Empire it selfe, and in fine bring them also into the subiection and succession of the Spaniard, as it appeareth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly by their proceedings now in hand. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this constraint and necessitie, we must submit our selues to the will and pleasure of our most iust God, and patiently expect and attend his ayde and deliuerance: Assuring our selues that God knoweth, that the Kings Maiestie of Bohemia, our most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord and Prince, and the States of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, together with the incorporated Countries thereunto, and the confederated Kingdomes with the same (notwithstanding they knew well that your Highnesse was diuerted and disswaded from him, by the Imperiall Councell; and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie hauing his Sword in Hand, and armed so long time before to oppose the enemie, and could also haue well preuented their proceedings,) he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer gaue nor offered cause of dislike in any manner whatsoeuer vnto your Highnesse; but to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, euer honoured, respected, and loued you, alwaies holding good correspondence with your Country: in the meane time omitting many good offers, and thereby hath done himselfe wrong.</p>
            <p>Touching our established Confederation, and our compulsiue Abdication of the Emperour <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2124:17"/>from this Crowne, and the election of our Kings Maiestie that now is; as also, of our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed defence, together with the deliberation, and of the incorporated Prouinces thereunto annexed: Wee haue had more then iust right and euident cause to proceede and continue therein; constantly perswading our selues, that we may well answer it both before God, and all other impartiall Princes and Potentates whatsoeuer, both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Empire, if we might obtaine any iust and lawfull audience in our cause.</p>
            <p>Likewise, to our great griefe, we are enformed, in what manner our Aduersaries, both within and without the Empire, most shamefully slaunder vs and our confederates: and as in former times the true professors of Christian Religion were vsed by Heathen Tyrants, so there can be no vntruths nor slanders deuised nor inuented, but the same are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed and layed vpon vs.</p>
            <p>And it is most vntruly giuen forth and reported, That we, by our Ambassadours, haue made a league with the Turke, haue correspondence, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and offered him free passage through this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Bohemia into the Empire; which is a most false and vntrue calumniation, for that neuer any such thing entered into our thoughts: as also that ours, and our Confederates Ambassadours, are yet but vpon their way towards the Portt or the Turks Court, and haue no other Commission nor Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions giuen vnto them, but onely to intreat vpon a good and friendly peace with them, as other
<pb facs="tcp:2124:17"/>Princes and Potentates of Christendome haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore done, and haue found great benefit hereby. And by this meanes the Empire of Rome shall by vs be better secured then euer it was heretofore by the House of Austria, who when it pleased them, without the knowledge and consent of any of the Princes-Electors, or this Kingdome, made warre with the Turke; and then againe intreated of peace, onely for their owne priuate commoditie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; which, when occasion serueth, is manifestly to be proued.</p>
            <p>And the bringing in of so many stranger-Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of diuers Nations, to ouerthrow and subiect these Countries bordering vpon the Turke, as they intend, will be no small meanes and occasion to moue and stirre the Turke to conceiue a iealousie against the Houses of Austria and Spaine; and so causing him to suspect their proceedings, he may peraduenture be moued in this dangerous time to attempt some great matter; it being done at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same time when the Ambassadours of these Countries and Prouinces are gone towards the Portt to intreat of Peace with him. Which if it should so happen, and fall out, (as God forbid it should) we protest before God and all the World, that we are not the procurers, but rather the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers thereof. And it is truely to be auouched, what great and large offers the Emperours Ministers haue made at the Portt, to moue and prouoke the Turke to make warre vppon the King of Hungarie that now is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:18"/>
            <p> As also, that they haue oftentimes boasted what intelligence and practises they haue in the Turkish Court, whereby they meane to preuaile against the confederated Countries, which in conuenient and due time shall manifestly appeare.</p>
            <p>Therefore in all humility, we beseech and intreat your Highnesse, as a prouident Protestant Prince, to be pleased wisely to consider of these things, and not in hostile manner to beginne warre with this Kingdome of Bohemia, and the incorporated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces thereof, but rather to consider and thinke vpon the poore innocent bloud which thereby might in these Countries, on both sides, be shedde; as also, that vpon extremity strange souldiers might be brought into the same, not onely to the vtter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and subvertion of those Countries, but also thereby to prouoke and stirre vp the wrath of God for the same against the wilfull offenders therein: Beseeching your Highnesse, rather to hold good correspondence and amitie with the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie our most gracious Lord, and those incorporated Countries; and to be perswaded what contentment you shall thereby giue vnto those Countries and their Inhabitants, and procure them to loue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you while they liue for the same.</p>
            <p>But if (contrary to our expectation) your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in hostile manner should attempt any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs, or our Confederates in High or Low Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia, your Highnesse must know, that we are bound by the Lawes of the Land, and our Confederacie, with our bodies, liues, and goods, against all men
<pb facs="tcp:2124:18"/>whatsoeuer, that shall in hostile manner inuade this Country and the incorporated Prouinces thereof, to defend the same; and protest, That our intent and meaning is not therein to doe or attempt any other thing, but onely with a full resolution (as the Lawes of God and Nature affords vs) to procure our owne defence, together with that of our Kings Maiestie, (and our auncient purchased freedomes and priuiledges) by vs and the incorporate Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces orderly chosen and crowned, together with our natiue country and friends: protesting before God, that neyther our Kings Maiestie, or any of vs, haue euer giuen and offered your Highnesse any iust cause of dislike. In respect whereof, we doe the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlier trust in the helpe and assistance of God, for the furtherance of our iust and lawfull cause, which wee will defend with our liues and goods, by the ayde of the new elected King of Hungaria, and the States of Hungaria, and Transiluania, our true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates: and thereby hope to free our selues from the oppression, seruitude, and slauerie which the Protestants bordering vpon the Riuer of Ense, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by faire promises, and partly by treacherous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises, and violent force of armes, are now constray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vndergoe, and are become subiect vnto the Duke of Bauaria; and bereauing themselues of their priuiledges, haue submitted their neckes vnder the mercie of the Emperour to rest at his deuotion; and hauing referred the libertie of their consciences and profession of true Religion to bare intercession and hopes, are forced and compelled to restore the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iners
<pb facs="tcp:2124:19"/>of their Country, and to entertaine and pay the Garrisons (or rather their cut-throats) therein placed, as a most intollerable yoake not to be borne, nor answerable before God and our posteritie; and by vs and ours, to the vttermost of our powers, by the ayde and assistance of God, to be reiected and withstood: leauing and committing the issue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to almightie God, most iust and most mercifull. To whom the sighs and teares of many thousand distressed soules are directed, &amp; piercing the clouds, ascend vnto his heauenly presence. And although men will neyther heare nor take pittie on them, we doubt not but that at the last, the Lord will cause and moue the stones in the streetes, and posts in the walls, to heare and answer them.</p>
            <p>Yet we cannot be perswaded, by any meanes, that your Electorall Highnesse wisheth or desireth that any of these euils should fall vpon vs, much lesse vpon your selfe. Wherewith beseeching almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to graunt your Highnesse a good counsell, with all health and happinesse both of bodie and soule; we euer remaine your Electorall Highnesse most bounden friends, and seruants to our power.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. N. the Priuie Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Officers and Iustices of the Kings Maiesty and Crowne of Bohemia.</signed>
               <dateline>Prague <date>the fourth, September 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:19"/>
            <head>Another Letter from the foresaid Counsellors, to the trayned Souldiers of Engern, and to some of the Cities &amp; Townes in the Electoral Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie of Saxonie.</head>
            <p>RIght Honourable, Worshipfull, and our most louing friends, we greet you wel. We doubt not but you haue already heard, that not long since, in the name and behalfe of our Country of Bohemia, we sent our Ambassadours to his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Highnesse of Saxonie, to desire of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, by commission from the Kings Maiestie of Bohemia, the renewing and confirmation of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient league and friendship, which on both sides (time out of mind) hath so long continued between them; and in this dangerous and most troublesome time, to strengthen and renew the same, crauing his Highnesse present resolution therein. Since when, by the relation of our sayd Ambassadours, we haue beene certified, that his Electorall Maiesty is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise disswaded and carried away by our Aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and the true intent of this Kingdome and the confederate Kingdomes and Countries with the same, wrested and construed to a wrong sence and contrary meaning; and that his Highnesse desire is, that we should restore and yeeld this Kingdome to the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and againe become his subiects; withall signifying, that he in regard there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had taken vpon him to put the Imperiall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission (concerning this Kingdome and the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated Prouinces of the same) in execution, as by
<pb facs="tcp:2124:20"/>his Highnesse preparation for warre, more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly appeareth; which his proceedings are very strange to vs, yet we leaue it to the prouidence of God, &amp; with patience attend the issue thereof, when it shall please him to effect the same.</p>
            <p>And we, together with these Countries, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready sufficiently declared, and by these presents declare before God and men, that whatsoeuer we haue done in our owne defence, or the abdication of the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and the election of our King that now reigneth, we haue so good grounds and reasons to warrant the same, that we are ready at all times to iustifie our proceedings both before God and man, being in conscience assured of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of our cause. And in the name of God are therefore fully resolued to defend and protect our King, whom we and these incorporate Countries (by vertue of our most ancient priuiledges) haue freely and voluntarily elected, crowned, and sacred; and by the helpe of God, and the vnited forces of our Confederates, will preserue and free his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties person and Countries, according to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties contract touching Religion, and other our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges (which with life and goods he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to maintaine, ratifie, and confirme) from all inuasion and oppression whatsoeuer; and cannot chuse but in conscience seeke to preserue both our selues and our posteritie from the vnsupportable Spanish yoake and slauery, whereat they and their adherents onely and specially ayme. And to that end determine to vse the ayde and assistance of the
<pb facs="tcp:2124:20"/>rest of the Protestant Princes. But at this present, these confederated Kingdomes and Countries, that alwaies haue continued in true amitie and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with the House and Electorall Principalitie of Saxonie, are not a little grieued that they should in hostile manner be inuaded by them; and yet doe not any wayes attribute the cause thereof to proceede from the true and peaceable Inhabitants of the same, but rather from diuers fugitiues of our owne Country, now at this present residing in the sayd Princes Electorall Court, and other wicked Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and counsellers wholly addicted vnto euill. Therefore, that the Inhabitants and Cities of the Electorate Principality of Saxonie, may well and truely vnderstand their owne and our good and true meanings and desires vnto peace and vnitie, &amp; how vnwilling we are to breake off or to abandon the peace, loue, and amitie long since made, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into hostile termes with them: We haue hereby aduertised, and in friendly manner aduise and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell them, to seeke by all meanes possible they may and can, to withdraw and diuert his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse from such extremes; and not to enter into any breach of ancient league and amitie with our King, his incorporated Prouinces and Confederate King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Countries, that neuer in any manner whatsoeuer haue giuen and offered his Highnesse or his Country any cause to the contrarie; but can iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proue that the said States of Bohemia, from the beginning of their defensiue warres, haue so much honoured and respected his Hignesse, that in regard
<pb facs="tcp:2124:21"/>thereof, they haue rather omitted and neglected ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good occasions to them offered, which they might well haue imbraced for their owne auaile. But (if to the contrary) we must be forced to doe that which we are loath to doe, and which the fruits and effects of warre afford, (although wholly against our wils) for the defence of our most gracious King and and Country, our wiues, children, lands, goods, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and priuiledges; we will not spare to do our vttermost therein, referring the issue thereof vnto Almighty God.</p>
            <p>Therefore once againe we request and desire our friends and allies, with whom we haue been so long time in good correspondence, friendship, and amity; to be pleased for the loue, zeale, and preseruation of the true Religion, the withstanding of the intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Spanish yoake, and the diuerting of the same from our posterity, with many other calamities that may ensue; earnestly and heartily to be the meanes to withdraw his electorall Highnesse from all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stile proceedings: and herewith commit them to the protection of the Almightie God. Dated in Prague the 4. of September, 1620.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Subscribed, The Counsellers and Officers to the Kings Maiestie and Crowne of</hi> BOHEMIA.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:2124:21"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE TO THE QVESTION: Whether the Emperour that now is, can bee Iudge in the BOHEMIAN Controuersie or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with the Extract taken out of</hi> the Acts of the Dyet at Auspurghe, in the yeare 1584: Concerning the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M.D.C.XX.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>